[SPEAKER_00]: How do you describe the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I guess one way is, it's that faculty of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, are we talking about māna?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was just thinking māna then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's talk about māna then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the dhamma part of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the very beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all things are preceded by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the forerunner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Excelled by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Made by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind by... as in mano.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in mano.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mano, mano, pubagama, mano, ceta, mano, maya.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's mano.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like an intellect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It deals with thoughts, rationale.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't really, I don't really think of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I was thinking a bit more as...
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, it's bodily in the sense, like the eye, the ear, the nose, it's part of the six domains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, that's what I mean, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dealing with thoughts, as in not necessarily understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's it, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't even, you can't even positively define, define māna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what manner is this?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there will be a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can discern it as manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you can't say, this is my eye that I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't imagine what manner is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can discern the basis of the eye on account of present sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is the mind conceivable without a thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you think mind...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a thought there, and that thought is made possible because manna is already... Yeah, but what is manna already there?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you know that there is mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Something making this possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, how can you know something without thinking it here?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then use that in a sentence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something makes this possible, when I can't even conceive something making this possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you open your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you know it's there?
[SPEAKER_00]: When all you can have is thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I guess it's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to say it's the necessary basis for... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a correct theoretical answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can it be a necessary basis?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, how can you even conceive that, even as a theoretical designation?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess because, if you rec... if you know that these thoughts, this... anything I could imagine,
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I mean, the first two-thirds of that sentence I could agree with, but how can you say
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is unreachable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're describing a direct experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: These thoughts are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're the true nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: What part of experience does correspond to that because of the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that abstract part.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just something that's beyond me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, how can you conceive it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's beyond you, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can even conceive a direction of it, it means it's within.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where's the problem now?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the problem now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Erm... Is the problem now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I guess this... this idea of being something beyond the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beyond the mind or beyond the thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like outside... thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like outside of thoughts, outside of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's what... the notion of mind lends itself to, this idea of something that is beyond the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what was the other...
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the common thread between this, what we're talking about, and the other two saṅkharas we were speaking about?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the nature of ignorance plus saṅkhara?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that result in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you mean the assumption of something outside?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's exactly what you've been doing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I ask you, what is the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: You start with a base of thought, but then provide an external description of a necessary basis, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is... How is that even conceivable?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you conceive the outside of the presently enduring thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the mind is the... the... the most fundamental appropriation and assumption, potentially, of assuming the external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can stop assuming external in regard to the body, stop assuming external even in regard to speech,
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceasing to assume externally in regard to your own thought, so you realize that's a slightly taller order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, keeping that in mind, what is the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is... well, can I say anything differently?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without... without... trying to designate something which is outside of my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the necessary basis then, for the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_00]: Body?
[SPEAKER_00]: More specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, feeling and perception?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's a different mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, oh, citta, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the necessary basis for... What is the necessary...
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, you cannot even conceive that there are eyes unless there are sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more specifically now, within that specific answer... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What aspect of thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that necessary basis for mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, saṅkhara, like, um, what else?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what characteristic of thoughts is the necessary basis for the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: What characteristic of the sights?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the necessary basis for existence of the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sort of thinking, like, the sort of peripheral thoughts, as opposed to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah, but... thoughts that I'm... More specifically, just take a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripheral thought, whichever.
[SPEAKER_01]: What internal characteristic of that thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: Characteristic?
[SPEAKER_01]: Property?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you finish the sentence?
[SPEAKER_00]: What characteristic?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, what internal characteristic?
[SPEAKER_00]: What internal property of the enduring thought is the necessary basis?
[SPEAKER_00]: For mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, based on which you can discern the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indirectly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't intentionally look at the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't intentionally think your way through to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can discern the property of the enduring thought to see that the mind cannot be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is that property?
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's related to other thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's an external property between the two thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Internal property of an enduring thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's... that it has manifested on its own?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To a degree, it is still.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same as sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that degree, they're independent.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the degree of their independence, they're unknowable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize that degree is the degree that comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you can exercise your ownership, you can think this, you cannot think that, on top of the degree of their resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there is absolutely not a trace of their resistance manifested, well, they wouldn't manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: There'd be nothing discernible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to that degree, that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not on the level of you thinking or you using the intellect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of turning the degree of the independence of those thoughts that kind of precede your intentionality.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't quite see how that... that clarifies the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it clarifies the mind in a sense that, eh... can...
[SPEAKER_00]: Resistance of a thought be outside of a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can the resistance of a thought be outside thoughtful?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you even define it even abstractly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Resistance of what without saying what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's inconceivable to misconceive it outside of the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's basically where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the manifestation of a thought
[SPEAKER_01]: In its impermanence?
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it seems to me, like, as if you're still looking for a positive definition of what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, I'm just still not quite seeing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... Well, can you see the resistance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you see the resistance of an enduring thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you see the resistance of an enduring thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that it has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you think it's relevant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you think the mind is the forerunner of all things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't see them as impermanent, it determines the whole direction of perceived permanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ownership, desire, lust, aversion, everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: If at that level, you don't ignore.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is an independence, resistance and own ability of a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind doesn't go down those pathways.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so then the necessary basis can be revealed indirectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's no neutral basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's either affected or unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you meant probably one other way I put this, but by
[SPEAKER_01]: Sort of, not ignoring the fact that these thoughts have just been thrown, you know, they're just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of reveals the fact that there is a necessary basis for those which isn't me.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, in order to avoid the danger of falling into abstract, because, as the Buddha said himself, the mind is hard to see, discern, under the ownership of, because it's fleeting, it's quicker...
[SPEAKER_00]: Think of it practically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think of it like this, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful of the body, right here, right now, present, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your body still here, alive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: While the body is here alive, are there also, simultaneous to it, but kind of independent of it, certainly not directly linearly related to it, are there also moods, enduring feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a feeling present?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'd say that's all, like, that's... that's kind of all... the only way I can know that there is a body there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different people approach differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a tier of an enduring body, you have another tier of an enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have another tier there, which is... What's your overall mood then, based on the present and your feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you describe that neutral mood as independent of your feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're differentiating mood and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, like how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're feeling neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your mood now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Positive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Negative?
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you feeling up for things or not up for things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Elated?
[SPEAKER_00]: Depressed?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel even, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel even, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you can't say feeling is even.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say feeling is pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can say that your mood based on your feeling is even.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what does that also involve?
[SPEAKER_00]: The description of evenness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It involves how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it involves how you perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is that thing that is inseparable from how you feel and how you perceive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another tier.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there is a fourth tier of what you're actually presently enduring thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: What dhammas are there?
[SPEAKER_00]: What phenomena have arisen on that most, sort of, in-point level, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the most general level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, general...
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the content, yeah, they're particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the nature, they're general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, you have a thought of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, if you're unmindful of it, it's a particular thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're mindful of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: It reveals the general nature of all phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are these four tiers that I just described?
[SPEAKER_00]: Satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the four foundations of mindfulness, and that's why any of them can serve to develop mindfulness to the extent necessary for the final knowledge, as in develop mindfulness to the extent necessary for the final uprooting of desire, lust and aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you practically develop the mind, or understand the mind, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Take the present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You said it's neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that also a thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take present enduring body.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your body posture currently?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sitting down.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your health status currently?
[SPEAKER_00]: Healthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Free from physical discomfort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, aren't those all those things that you just designated described also thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's four tiers.
[SPEAKER_00]: That all contain each other, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, take the theory of thought, presently enduring body, so you have a thought of seated posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to have that thought, unless there is the actual physical body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to have that thought, unless there is also awareness of, basically, the whole experience in regard to that body, which is already how you feel and what you perceive?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that thought also perceived?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't the perception also felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're all just...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's four aspects of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever you look, they're all four there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look at them rightly, exactly, you look at one, the other three are in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why any of them can serve for the mindfulness to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why any of them can serve for you to uproot assumption of external to what you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Can you assume external of your present enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that even conceivable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no, not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can imagine something, but then that's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that is within what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have the present enduring feeling, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yesterday, I felt a bit different, but I'm still... On the basis of today.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of today, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not dwelling on it sufficiently enough that it's inconceivable, you keep conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to understand māna and dhammas, develop mindfulness of the body properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to understand mindfulness of the body properly, develop mindfulness of dhammas and māna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you'll be understanding the resisting aspect, and you'll be understanding the designation aspect of it, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because can you know that there is, as I said,
[SPEAKER_00]: That there is a seated body here and now, unless there is also thought of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, even that question, unless there is also thought, implies there's something else with the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that something else, unless that's another thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that thought outside of your thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: All there is, is thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: All there is, is thoughts that resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that designate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The designation part is where intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where you intend and follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if all exists is thoughts, people say, oh, it's all in my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, it's all in your head that also resists you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means that you can't own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: He's what the body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there were no body resisting it, that is also being thought while it's resisting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's say...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might say...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm thinking of the body, and so that's a thought, but then that... then you might think, well, that's a thought of the body, which is something that's not a thought, but that's... How could I know that if it's not a thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's you assuming... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: How could I not... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can't basically get outside of this... That's you not practicing satipaṭṭhānas one within the other, but
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think the linear arrangement of methods means you don't understand what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you have a thought of the body, or you might... that thought of the body might start with a more of a resisting aspect of the thought of the body, which is this body enduring here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that presently enduring basis of the body, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is also presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the things that now you see correctly within the container of the present enduring body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start looking at the container of the present enduring body, you say, oh, so this is the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to be careful now, because that designation, if you misconceive it, it can then assume external to itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in you say, oh, this body is a thought, or even more blatantly, this body is just a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it implies then,
[SPEAKER_00]: This is just a thought, and then there is that which is a real body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you even finish the sentence?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is that which is the real body, unless that's already a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're saying, there is a thought, and there is a real thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a thought, and there is a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: This whole mind matter thing is so deeply rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the entire world, as the Buddha said, falls into approval of the matter or disapproval of the matter, as in affirmation or denial, as in
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you say, rather than...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having the idea of this thought of the body, which then leads one to think of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, instead of thinking in that linear way, I guess, it's rather... you can only understand what matter is, or what the body is, through that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes, but even that won't be... like, see, if you... if you can... if you still carry on, like, an implicit assumption that I can understand real matter through the thought, that is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the aspect of real?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you know that, unless you're thinking it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's assumed as an external reality that precedes your thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is the real.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole idea of Mahāyāna, you know, the...
[SPEAKER_00]: The reality behind the conventions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you even speak of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless it's another convention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when people don't know how to escape this, don't know how to deal with the problem of assumption, so then they blame the designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say the conventions, designations, words, names, nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you stop doing it, you get to the real reality that you just named.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize naming is not a matter of choice either, because whenever there is a degree of resistance, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just named it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a degree of resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not a new.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The target understands the extent of designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Designation just means something's been recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't necessarily mean you've given it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're labeling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, labeling, naming come out of it, but it's far down the road.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, just the recognition that something's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: People don't know how to deal with the problem, so then they try to identify it with labeling and naming, which is easily dismissible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just refrain from naming, and that's the reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't refrain from thought that's already a designation in itself, that resists you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, you can't refrain from... You can refrain from engaging upon thought in a certain manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't refrain from having thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those thoughts are already designated to that extent, that they resist you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they do resist you because, again, they appear to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: For you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness of the body is then mindfulness of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the thoughts properly, as I said, to the... discerning the extent the thought resists you, or it implies fundamental resistance, which is resistance of the senses and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness of the thoughts properly, means mindfulness of the body properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everything in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: In between being feelings and moods.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all of that is inconceivable without feelings and moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can you can pick the aspect you want to do, but you'll be developing all them if you're doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't need to kind of look at the other one and go, you know, you just... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're comparing them, you have none.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, another thing to mention, it's like, so you say, okay, so this is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have a thought of this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't help but imply that there is that outside of this thought from which this body has come, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, that's no matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't remove that implication by choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will uproot the implication
[SPEAKER_00]: By including it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, exactly, to the extent it assumes external, to that extent, exclude itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this pertains to this thought, that's within the domain of thoughts, gratuitously, somehow, implies that it's outside of this domain of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I can conceive anything outside of my senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, that's, again, it's in the same
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same nature, same principle, what we described, when you think you're accessing the objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can access is your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can access is your senses being affected by different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, different things means outside of my senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the implication.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you fully understand it, so you're not to go, oh, I must stop, stop thinking this implication.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop thinking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I should include it within the necessary container of the present enduring body, not exclude it as something outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the assumption aspect of it fades.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But thought in itself was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even a wrong thought is not a problem in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is the, the significance that the, that gratuitously carries.
[SPEAKER_00]: Significantly, there is a real reality behind my reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you discern any of that, any scope of that domain, unless you're thinking it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is fine to think it, but it's not fine that
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think it, you think that your thought is second to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the only way to know it is to think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically it's the order that's different, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That perverted order at the most fundamental level of dhamma and māna, māna is the forerunner of all things, pervert the order, māna is the forerunner of all perverted things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perversion of lust, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You approve...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, polluted stream on top of the mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how far down you go, it's gonna carry the same pollution.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how much, how hard you're trying to purify the water at the lower points, your work is endless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not uprooting it at the source.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you go and find the source, and clear the pollution in the very source, and then you don't have to worry about...
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter even if it turns into a whole ocean later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you know it cannot be polluted because you have cleaned up the source.
[SPEAKER_00]: And dissociate the mind and the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mind is definable by the resistance of the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present enduring thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present enduring thought of the body, present enduring thought of the feeling, present enduring thought of the mind, the mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present enduring thought of impermanence, present enduring thought of suffering, even present enduring thoughts of you can't own any of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't own any of this and the thoughts that I can't own any of this are unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I understand them as unownable, no idea of ownership can be attained in regard to anything inferior to them, anything within them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so all perceptions, sights, sounds,
[SPEAKER_01]: Smells this, touches?
[SPEAKER_01]: All... that's all secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's said the five senses meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like they...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think many people today tend to think that that's the kind of building blocks and then they come and they meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're constructed together and then reality gets constructed by the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you conceive anything that's pre-reality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you even theorize about pre-reality unless you're theorizing it in the real time, here and now, which is your reality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here you are, using the means of this reality, which is the means of resisting thoughts that designate, to describe that which precedes this resistance and designation, and somehow assume the validity of that world that's utterly inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you assuming the axis, that's how these things exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said that four great elements find the footing in your experience,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you conceive them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give them the being through your misconceiving, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, they cannot appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can only resist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already designated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, present enduring feeling, you can
[SPEAKER_00]: Approach is a present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm feeling like this, while I'm doing this, while I'm feeling like this, while I'm talking, feeling like this, while I'm breathing, I'm feeling like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm still feeling the same while we are sitting and discussing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can approach a present enduring feeling, it will also be a present enduring thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is a thought, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, can you have that thought if there isn't present in your feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you know the present in your feeling if there isn't... if it isn't a thought, if it isn't an image, if it isn't a dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there's a tendency to think that the feeling is a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're comparing the approaches, you're not doing either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the way to avoid that is to include the feeling within the thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Include your need to compare.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the present enduring feeling or within any present enduring tear, within any present enduring anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can think about the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of being mindful of the present enduring body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can think about feeling on the basis of present enduring thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever way you rooted your mindfulness, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it will have to be rooted in one of these four things.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing outside of these tiers that you can think or experience that's not within one of them, which implies all the other ones.